Good afternoon everyone.
Welcome you all. I mean welcome you all
on this international MSME day.
We have with us Mr. Rakesh Verma. He's
head of finance from Neon Laboratories.
We also have with us Mr. Ajay Thakur.
He's head BSE and SME. He's the man
basically behind as you see a lot of
SMEs getting listed in the stock
exchange.
Today is a great day for all of us and
this is the fifth anniversary of
international MSME day which was started
by United Nations.
Just to give you a brief today MSME
accounts for about 90% of the
enterprises in India. Today it
contributes about 45% of the Indian
exports and roughly it's around 38% of
the country's GDP
and roughly around 100 million people
are I mean employed out here. This is a
great sector which is coming up. It also
has a lot of socio-economic objective.
For example,
it provides a huge amount of employment.
It's I mean high growth of output,
export promotions, I mean enabling
entrepreneurs spirits. These are some
real great things which the MSME and SME
sectors is coming up.
And even our government is supporting
these initiatives a big time in terms of
startup India, skill India, make in
India. All these opportunities out
there.
So today we we are going to discuss in
terms of SME as a segments or SME and
MSME as segments. What are the
opportunities out there? How we can help
them to grow? And from ICICI Lombard
General Insurance Company of course
we'll talk about in terms of how ICICI
Lombard can be a partner in in terms of
the risk coverage out there. So Ajay,
the first question to in terms of can
you just share a brief insights of the
SME sector?
Thanks
for inviting me for this event. I think
MSMEs are the backbone of an economy in
any country.
And because of their importance today we
are celebrating global MSME day and it
is therefore very much essential and
important for all the stakeholder to
ensure a healthy and sustainable growth
of
macro, small and medium enterprises. I
think if India has to grow in double
digit
then the well-being of macro, small and
medium enterprises are very much
required and I think now a lot of
association,
ICICI Lombard for example today or for
that matter BSE has today celebrated
global MSME day and we are inviting all
the experts to ensure that they properly
guide the macro, small and medium
enterprises so that the macro
enterprises can grow to the to a small
level and a small level should grow to
the medium level and after that they
should become large corporate especially
in the country like India where we have
to give
employment to almost 5 crore people
every year and we have got
you know
demographic dividend but it should be a
boon for us rather than it becoming a
curse and therefore macro, small and
medium enterprises which gives a lot
of employment,
we have to ensure that they should grow
in a healthy manner. Great Ajay. Thanks.
Thanks Ajay. Rakesh, what's your thought
in terms of how are SMEs helping in the
growth story of India? The thing is that
being our present Prime Minister, first
of all I thank to invite me on that.
When our Prime Minister declared
Atmanirbhar Bharat,
how a person how a country can become
Atmanirbhar? If our giants are only
making the India growing, it cannot make
Atmanirbhar. A small sectors, micros,
medium and small enterprises should come
into the play play of role and then only
it can come to the
that each and nook and corner the
production should be there, services
should be there so that
employment generation can be done,
productions can be done
to the ground level as a as a country we
have a population which is second
largest in the world. So wait for them
employment is the major thing and
MSME only can create a major employment
in everywhere. If a large unit is there,
it can be it will be concentrated to
some area only but MSME can contribute
it to every each and nook and corner.
That's my perception.
Great Rakesh. I mean great concept of
Atmanirbhar. I mean I'll just a little
bit go deep into that in terms of
Atmanirbhar, how does SME manage or MSME
manage his
Atmanirbhar in growth along with its
risk because he also grow many grows he
also carries risk around that. How he
manages that? What's your thought around
that?
There are many things in it. When if a
if there are many
startups are coming up.
If startups are coming up the startups
are promoted under MSME.
If a person is
main thing is that which Atmanirbhar is
given that can be self-employed.
If a self a person becomes a
self-employed, he doesn't he becomes a
self-employed. He makes others employed.
He generates the employment under him.
That makes makes that the person is
known and
if in a rural place of some engineer is
there, if that engineer
sees that I want to be an employee of an
organization, it his education will be
limited to that only. But if we think
that I will set up a small unit over
here
he himself will become an entrepreneur
and he will generate the employment in
his surrounding.
So Absolutely. that will make its
Atmanirbhar things will better and this
will grow in
clusters and clusters it will go inside
the team. If a person thinks that I am
engineer I'll go to a TCS or somewhere,
he will be restricted to there. But now
a self-employment will be generated in
there.
Great Rakesh. I mean just to help even
the SMEs and MSMEs in terms of managing
their risk, ICICI Lombard is the first
organization or insurance company in
this country which have created a
digital platform called
SME.icicilombard.com
wherein they can go and
I mean cover their risk and buy any of
the coverages what they want from the
business point of view. So both in terms
of growth as well as in terms of the
risk management, we always play role in
terms of partner. I mean how we can help
our SMEs in terms of growing their I
mean businesses out there. Ajay, I mean
in terms how is technology and
innovation helping value creation in
Indian SMEs or MSMEs? Any thoughts
around that?
I think digitization and automation
these are the two very important pillars
for the growth of
small, medium enterprises or for any
other enterprises. I think COVID-19 has
taught us
to you know implement digitization at
earliest. Okay. If you can't bring the
digitization in the
company then with you know cutthroat
competition you can't survive. So I
think digitization as well as automation
has to be given a lot of importance in
each and every enterprise irrespective
of whether it's macro, small or medium
enterprise. At the same time I think we
need to inculcate a lot of awareness
among macro, small and medium
enterprises that today
digitization or automation has become
very cost-effective. Okay, it's no
longer a very you know costly business.
There are a lot of
you know agencies out there who are
providing digitization to the macro
small and medium enterprises in a very
cost-effective manner. At the same time
government has also taken a lot of
initiative towards the digitization. Not
only that, even there are some funds
available or which has been created by
the government whereby your digitization
costs are being taken care of. So I
think macro, small and medium
enterprises have to see and ensure that
immediately they should take the help of
digitization for their future growth.
Only then their survival will be
possible. Otherwise I think the survival
will become very tough.
Well said Ajay. I mean we could also see
I mean a lot of digitization I mean in
terms of automations happening in SMEs
and their openness to digitization out
there. I mean from a physical processes
to a digital processes,
the openness is there in terms of
digital payments even also we are seeing
a lot of growth around happening out
there and that's a key in terms of
scalability of SMEs that we have seen
because the biggest challenge of SMEs in
terms of scaling of different stages of
the evolution of the lifespan of the
SMEs and
these are big tools in terms of helping
them to grow in the numbers and grow in
the Not not only that, even digital
payment systems are in place. Okay.
Today there are so many e-commerce
platform
through which many of these companies
can sell their
you know products. So I think you know
as a country also we are moving towards
digitization and
automation and I think every every small
and medium enterprise should start
imbibing
digitization.
And what are the key challenges you are
seeing from the SME sector point of
view? I think it's the lack of
awareness. That's more. I think you know
today we are talking sitting in Mumbai
or some other tier one city. Again tier
one cities, you know there are many
agencies which are creating awareness
but let me tell you there is a big set
of macro, small and medium enterprises
which jokingly we can say in Bharat
that is tier two and tier three cities
where we need to create a lot of
awareness. I have been traveling through
across the country throughout the
various cities and I still I am seeing
there is a lack of awareness among tier
in the tier two, tier three cities where
I still people have or the entrepreneurs
have not digitized their systems.
So I think that we need to ensure that
those people should also be brought into
the fold and you know,
a lot of work should be done in those
areas.
Rakesh, what's your thoughts in terms of
key challenges for the SME sector?
Three challenges in that the awareness.
Major basically what is happening
Yes, when I say Atmanirbhar is there, it
is going not in the rural areas. It is
not only urban areas only. It is going
rural areas also. But the awareness of
digitalization which Mr. That also told
that that awareness should come to that
level and they should feel that it is
secure.
Basically, man, when a new technology
comes, the person is very much hesitant
to adopt it.
So, he should be aware that yes, I I
should adopt it and he should feel that
it is secure. Let's go government of
India is taking many initiatives. Many
programs are being carried out. So, when
the awareness will come and the safety
and security features will be aware to
them. So, digitalization platform will
be generated. Not only in financial
sectors, in marketing sectors also
digitalization has came to much a lot
way. But many of things say that
if a product is being sold on digital
platform, the person thinks that yes, if
yeah, I will get that product properly
or not.
So, that awareness, the brand
the
mobilization will take some time, but it
will it has its own hurdle.
But
everyone has to be rest assured that
time tested everything will go on run at
some time.
So, one thing One thing Mr. Moorthy I
would like to add is this digitalization
is not a one-time process. Okay. Now
that you know, now
you know, every
day we are seeing you know, some or
other new innovation happening. So, we
need to the promoters of the small
medium enterprises have to be alert.
Number two, uh
you know, we are still seeing a lack of
skills
especially in the tier two tier cities.
So, we need to bring a lot of skilled
manpower into the system. Okay. We can't
go along with semi-skilled or unskilled
people in the
country. So, for example, this is a very
big gap that what we are seeing that
skilled people are still not in tier two
tier three cities. So, how they will
adopt digitalization? That is a big
issue. So, we need to develop these
skill sets among those employees which
are working in these
you know,
micro small and medium enterprises and
improve their skill sets so that they
keep on adopting this technology.
Great in terms of hearing in terms of
digitalization, automation and
unavailability of the skill set with the
different local corner of the countries
and of course awareness is a big
challenge from the SME point of view.
Sticking to the point of awareness, we
also have seen
lot of SMEs, MSMEs today are uninsured
across the country. If you see, I mean
many of them have not taken insurance or
other basically the risk coverage. In
the journey of growth,
I mean some or other they're missing the
I mean in terms of how do they cover the
risk which can actually derail their
business models. What's the thought
process in terms of Mr. Rakesh in terms
of how do you create awareness around
SMEs on those lines?
See, basically first of all, every
individual has to see that yes, whatever
he has, whatever he is running,
he should have a second lining that he
should insure himself. If that awareness
is in it is in the self, then it can
come to a uh
the insurance companies may do the
propaganda, but if the owner if he
himself think that yes, if he wants to
insure himself or not, that awareness he
has to be brought himself. Yes, many ads
are coming in it that
now you can insure anything anything and
anywhere. You can insure anything. So,
if that is there and
if a person is having a
majorly it was earlier it was that how
to reach to an insurance company. That
was a a problem at earlier times. But
now being a digital platform, it has
become that you can buy from your mobile
phone also. Your insurance policy can be
on going online. You can purchase for
any vehicle or anything any any assets
if you want to purchase, you can do it
online. When the purchase
it has happened also that if you go to a
store also, over there also you can
purchase on while purchasing that asset
only you get the insurance policy
attached to it.
So, basically
insurance companies, but self
Everyone should know that yes, whatever
I am having, I can be insured. If a
person is
having a car current policy than that.
Then it goes to the factory. In factory
also many are many are
not knowing
what level and what things I should
insure and what policies should be
insured. Person should think that yes, I
want to insure my any risk
at every level. If that awareness comes
from the self, then it can be insured at
the level.
Great great Rakesh in terms of helping
customers, MSMEs and SMEs across the
country to
self-insure themselves, we have created
this platform itself which is a very
easy tool. I mean
SME.icicilombard.com
wherein the customers or the I mean the
I mean SMEs can go and buy simple
insurance products from that side. What
we have realized is
I mean when a startups happen or MSME or
SME starts, maybe initially
they are not
risk aware or they're not risk averse,
but they're not risk aware. I mean with
gradually with businesses growing, with
employees getting added, we have seen
that adoption of buying insurance has
started seeing adoptions around that.
And I'm sure eventually it will grow up
faster out there. What's the thought
process Rakesh in terms of you have seen
even for employees, I mean today
startups have average 20-30 employees
and their families associated and
they're critical mass for their I mean
organization I mean for the organization
growth, these are critical employees
which works day in day out for them.
And we have seen even some of these SMEs
have not even
I mean
taken group health insurance for the
employees. Do foresee there's a big
opportunity in terms of do foresee that
that awareness of big opportunity
Nowadays nowadays it is there that HR
keeps in its policy and when he is being
appointed or when the interview is
taken, the person asks what are the
benefits I get from that employment.
So, if an
employer is having some type of policy
or group medical policy or group
personal accident policy on its role,
then that is a
that is attracting an employee to join
that organization because nowadays it is
seen that only not a CTC which he is
getting is not enough for him. He thinks
that what is securing myself if some
eventually happens to me. So, that has
that
awareness has already came into the
employees who are going for search of
job and one of the question is raised by
an employee who is candidate is raised
to the HR that what is the facilities
you are giving in type of insurance. So,
every organization should at least do
one thing that medical
GP should be covered because it's a
manufacturing unit or it's a service
industry is a person is moving from one
place to another, accident may have
occurred. So, at least if some sort of
group personal accident policy is taken
by each and every person which is to
some extent mandatory to the
manufacturing unit by the government of
India also. But that awareness was not
there. Now employees are getting aware
and they ask for that also. And
insurance companies do come with
innovative ideas in the group personal
accident policy, group medical policy
with covering everything at anywhere and
any locations. That is promoting it. In
terms of Ajay ji, in terms of one of the
theme we have seen in terms of a lot of
SMEs, MSMEs going for listing
and how has been their journey and how
do you see their risk going up when they
are getting listed?
See,
of course, in last 10 years of launch of
SME platform, it was not an easy
journey. You know, in India, there is a
lack of financial literacy and
you know, mostly the promoters are
technocrats and
you know,
they don't understand. In fact, equity
has very least understood by you know,
most of the people in country and
especially in the promoters
small and medium enterprises, they these
the promoters of these small and medium
enterprises, they think that post
listing compliances increases a lot and
therefore they become very hesitant to
come for listing.
Many of the time these promoters think
that you know,
listing is the game of uh only the large
corporates.
Uh so, now we are trying to create a lot
of awareness. In fact, in last 10 years
we have done two times excellent
seminars. We have signed MOU with
various state governments and
financial institutions also and we are
using their infrastructure to reach to
those promoters and try to explain them
the benefits of listing.
So, it has been a continuous phenomenon
and almost we have met 36,000 SME
promoters across the country. But still
the conversion has been less. In total,
we have 376 SMEs listed. Uh they have
raised almost 4,000 crores from primary
market, another 1,500 crores from
secondary market and the market
capitalization that they have created I
mean to say the valuation that they have
created
is almost 50,000 crores and it has
touched all-time high of 55,000 crores.
So, these SMEs post listing have
unlocked their value and the promoters
need to understand that listing is a
process of unlocking the value.
At the same time, so over the time when
I have seen the corporate governance and
all those practices starts coming into
the company. The
The unlocking of the valuation happens
very fast. You know, investors start
trusting into the company. Not only
that, the promoters also need to
understand that listing also give them a
lot of credibility and visibility and
that also helps in expanding their
businesses and also we have seen in the
listed space the interest rate is lower
than for those companies which are in
the unlisted space. So, there are
various benefits, but of course as I
have
told you in the beginning itself that
the lack of financial literacy and
because the equity market has been very
least understood, so therefore there is
a difficulty in convincing the promoters
to get listed. But all those SME
promoters who got listed, they
experiences a huge value getting
unlocked and
they feel that they have done the best
thing by getting themselves listed.
Thanks Ajay. I mean you've been a part
of the journey of creating and unlocking
the value of SMEs from a journey of SMEs
to mid-corporates to corporates.
I believe that's a journey every SME
should go through in terms of when India
is shining and the economy is booming up
across the country out there. But have
you seen in terms of the perception of
risk changing with the listing happening
or their size increasing? I mean have
you seen those aspects out there? The
only issue that I have faced is till the
time of listing. Till the
time of listing I have to convince a
lot. But post listing I have hardly seen
the promoters calling me or telling me
that they are facing any issue. So, till
the time of listing they keep on telling
me sir this is your company, you hand
hold us, you take care of us. But post
listing I have hardly received any call
from the listed companies promoters.
Okay, they have not faced any issue.
Hardly ever once or twice they have
called me to take the guidance, but they
have not faced any problem. At the time
of listing while convincing I have seen
the promoters very much worried about
the compliances, but let me tell you on
the SME platform there is a lot of
reduction in the compliances. You know,
it's not quarterly audit filing, it's
half-yearly unaudited results filing and
yearly audited results filing. So, we
have relaxed the compliance requirement
on the SME platform, but let me tell you
30% of our SME that comes to around 144
SME have already migrated to the main
board of the stock exchange. Knowing
that the migration into the main board
will increase their compliances, but now
they are not worried of compliances.
They feel that doing compliances
will increase their valuation and they
will get more funds for their expansions
and for the growth of the business.
So, I think that's the mindset we really
need to change the mindset. We need to
you know, have many hands and many
voices talking onto the street about the
benefits of listing and telling the
promoters that it's in their benefit to
get their company listed. I think if
this thing starts happening
widely in the country, I think many of
the companies will get listed. We'll see
5,000 to 10,000 SMEs getting listed and
India becoming the
biggest country in terms of market
capitalization. Today we are number five
or number six. I think if 5,000 SMEs
will get listed, you will become the
number one company in terms of market
capitalization in the world and then you
will find India really shining and then
you will find employment getting really
created.
Absolutely. I mean Ajay ji, I mean
absolutely
in the right path. I mean I'm sure India
will be going on those paths in terms of
dream we have.
So, coming back Rakesh in terms of one
of the challenges we have seen in terms
of SMEs is uh
I mean in in terms of claims
damage for them a small claim is also a
big cash flow issue out there.
Do you foresee in terms of the claims of
SMEs being seen a different way or a
faster settlement? What's your views
around that?
Basically SMEs are going mouth
uh
hand to mouth in financial sectors. If
any claim is there, that is going
it is debiting
uh working cycle.
Means basically working capital is being
disturbed.
If the claims are settled in proper
timely manner and it will not derail
their activities.
Claim has already a claim has happened,
it has derailed them.
If the claims are delayed, that will
derail
their working capital cycle and which
may have a business problem also. The
cycle will be disturbed. So, claim
should be fastened to them. At least a
part payment should be done to them upon
the initial survey some if if it is
found that yes, genuinely the claim is
there. If claim is entertainable, at
least 30% 40% should be reimbursed to
him on the undertaking that claim
doesn't means
that the funds are allocated to them,
the working cycle is not disturbed. And
the fact I know that if the private
sector has came into it and the claim
settlement is being a fastest way.
But then too it should be seen that the
surveyors do not hurdle it anywhere. And
the next to that the employer or the
business owner also has to
submit the documents and everything to
process in the same.
Yes, claim settlement fastest will
improve upon
that.
So,
I mean to support SMEs and MSMEs across
the country, we at ICICI Lombard uh
uh
we say claim is the ultimate truth. I
mean
and we understand that even if it is a
small claim or any size of claim, it do
affect their cash flow. So, we we drive
in terms of ensuring that all small
claims to be settled within or offer for
settlement is given within 10 days of
the claim of the survey report I mean
the document being submitted. Apart from
that to support them in terms of large
claims, we also do on account payment so
that their businesses do not get stopped
or their business cycle continues even
if the claim has happened. As an
industry we always believe that
insurance industry is a partner to SMEs
in terms of their growth
growth and of course are partners to
share their risk. And apart from that we
also do a lot of activities in terms of
mitigation of the risk. I mean it is not
only to pay claims on time, we also play
part in terms of reducing their risk or
mitigation of the risk. For example, we
do a lot of value added services,
electrical audits in terms of risk
inspections. We do a lot many things so
that we ensure that their business is
not affected in terms of
risk that's affecting us. So, I mean
great discussions, great insights from
both Ajay as well as Rakesh
in terms of SMEs I mean in terms of
growth journey, how they have been a
part of
India shining or growth of Indian
economy. Thanks so much for the sparing
your time and thanks so much for sharing
your insights. And we all believe that
uh
India being shining and India I mean
SMEs being contributing around 40% of
the GDP, the days are not far then when
SMEs will contribute the max to the
Indian economy. Thank you so much.
Thanks Mohanty. It's It's a pleasure to
be Thank you. Thank you. Thank you so
much.
Hey!